<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Diving out of meta</title>
    <description>I am Simon Janin. I write articles on blockchain technology (especially Ethereum), computer science and technology, rationality, self-improvement and social issues.
</description>
    <link>http://simonjanin.ch/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://simonjanin.ch/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 27 Mar 2016 20:41:45 +0200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 27 Mar 2016 20:41:45 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.2.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Post-Homestead Ethereum -- forwards and backwards</title>
        <description>&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/58YoiOdHVKY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The PDF of the presentation is &lt;a href=&quot;/downloads/Ethereum_post-Homestead-presentation.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 27 Mar 2016 22:13:37 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://simonjanin.ch/cryptocurrency/ethereum/2016/03/27/Post-Homestead-Price-explosion-network-effect-analysis.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://simonjanin.ch/cryptocurrency/ethereum/2016/03/27/Post-Homestead-Price-explosion-network-effect-analysis.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>cryptocurrency</category>
        
        <category>ethereum</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>DeepMind vs. Lee Sedol - predictions of what could be the most significant AI event of the century.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In my previous article on the topic in September, I presented what I believed what going to be profoundly important for A.I and the game of Go: Google DeepMind’s.
I took the risk to predict that machines would be able to beat professional players with 3 or 5 years, or less. Although my prediction was mathematically correct, What happened completely exceeded my expectations: Deepmind’s AlphaGo (the Go playing engine they developped) beat Fan Hui (2 Dan professional) with a score of 5-0!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In January, Deepmind announced that their engine will face Lee Sedol – arguably one of the best Go players to have ever lived – in a 5-games battle.
Today, after watching Demis Hassabis’ talk on their latest advances in the field (with a focus on AlphaGo), I feel ready to make another prediction; namely who I believe will win the match: &lt;strong&gt;AlphaGo&lt;/strong&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not a popular opinion among Go players, especially the professionals.
My reasonning is the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AlphaGo’s October version that faced Fan Hui was trained on only 100’000 KGS high dans games. A Korean professional reviewing AlphaGo’s games even said that it played in a typically Japanese style (unofficial interpretation: good looking shape that often lacks severity, or basically a mediocre move that looks nice); western players have been extremely influenced by Japanese Go, and this isn’t surprising that this would show in the games they play on KGS. But today Korean and Chinese players rule the game. This leads me to believe that there is a major room for improvement just by feeding AlphaGo more games; especially higher-quality games – typically from Korean and Chinese professionals. This should be able to significantly improve AlphaGo’s evaluation function.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;At the time of the encounter with Fan Hui (in October 2015), Deepmind’s strength was around 3000 ELO points – based upon standard Bayesian inference on its games against the strongest Go engines in the world (Zen and Crazy Stones); this method for gauging strength becomes extremely accurate as the number of games played grows. The presentation below shows very well that the team at Deepmind is fully aware of this and uses very strict metrics to measure improvement. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AlphaGo can play against itself millions of times in a single day: an amount of experience that no human can ever top. Furthermore, it’s evident that Google is going to devote massive ressources to what could be the most important event in 21st century A.I History.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Humans get tired. AlphaGo won’t. The games will last 4 to 5 hours! Only bugs are to be feared; but then again, I trust Google’s engineers have performed a high level of testing, although the deadlines are very tight.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To finish, it’s likely that they will improve the search and scoring function significantly. If so, this could result in a major overall improvement.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It’s also unclear to me what kind of hardware they are allowed to use during the match. Because I would not be surprised if they upgraded it; this could also play an important role.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They could even select an opening that Lee Sedol doesn’t feel confortable with when they play black, while he doesn’t have this advantage against AlphaGo. But I don’t think this will be necessary.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/4fjmnOQuqao&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why my money is on AlphaGo. To be honest I wasn’t sure until I watched the presentation above.
Here are how I evaluate the possible outcomes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AlphaGo wins 5-0: 24%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AlphaGo wins 4-1 or more: 46%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AlphaGo wins 3-2 or more: 65%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AlphaGo loses: 35%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2016 02:45:35 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://simonjanin.ch/learning/2016/03/02/DeepMind-vs-Lee-Sedol.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://simonjanin.ch/learning/2016/03/02/DeepMind-vs-Lee-Sedol.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>learning</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The art of Learning</title>
        <description>Notes article learning.

In the last two months, I spent my entire time -- literally -- studying and learning. Out of this intense experience, I believe there are many lessons that can be learned.
In this article, I will try to lay down some of the principles for successful learning. Some are paramount, while others are more a matter of personal taste or minors tweaks to reach optimal performance.

First, we will focus on the most important aspect: the why. Why are we learning/studying? Willpower can get us only so far, and unsustainable activities usually don&#39;t give us enough time to truly master a skill. More than anything else, the sheer amount of hours is what separates the expert from the average practitioner. But obviously the expertise-hours relation is simply a correlation, what counts in the end is the amount of *work* that has been done. Physically, work is defined as the amount of Force ($$F$$) times velocity  ($$\mathbf{v}$$) during a given period ($$t_1$$ to $$t_2$$); or equivalently, the amount of Force over a Curve ($$C$$).

$$W =  \int_{t_1}^{t_2}\mathbf{F} \cdot \mathbf{v}dt =\int_C \mathbf{F} \cdot d\mathbf{s}$$

*Sorry about that. I just had to put some math in there.*

This equation tells us the importance not only of how much time we spend, but also at which *velocity*. This reminds of the saying: 

&gt; Perfect practice makes perfect

In the physical work analogy, perfection is measured by how much we learn at each instant (the velocity).

In yet another sense, the path we take is critical because a movement that comes back to its original point has, in physics, done absolutely no work!

###Focus on the why
Why are you learning whatever you set to learn? What impact does it have on your life, on your relationships, on your wellbeing? Connecting our learning goals to a larger vision helps stay motivated when times get rough.

&gt; I do this, because [..]
&gt; This is what I was meant to do. This makes me a [..]
&gt; Once I have learned this, I will be able to [..]

Those are great sentences you can tell yourself to remember why what you do is important.
It&#39;s even easier to stay motivated when your goals have a strong social component: having one&#39;s actions impact other human-beings we care about is perhaps the biggest reason why billions of people get out of bed everyday; be it a mother who cares for her childs, or a worker who fears the judgment of his colleagues if he arrives just a few minutes later than them at work.
If those social incentives are not present, it&#39;s really important to manifacture them: find partners who have similar goals, and who can hold you accountable. This holds for waking up early, as well as for how much work you put in and for pushing you to do things that you keep on putting off.

###Reverse Engineering
If you had to learn how to build a car in a day, how would you do it?
Would you pick a book on physics, mechanical engineering, calculus, linear algebra? Or would you take a car and try to reverse engineer it, taking it appart component by component -- learning to 


Reverse engineering.
*What do successful people do?
*How do they spend their time?
*What are their standards.

Motivation: start with why
Objective: start with the end in mind. Understand what is required first, then optimize the path to get there.

Social incentives and structure. The reason why billions people wake up each days, and lack thereof is also why people can&#39;t get up from bed: no social incentive.
Collaboration. Challenge each other. Teach to learn. Learn to teach. Learn to impress. Learn to compete. Learn to connect. Learn to help.
White board. Group dynamics.
Personality types. Introverts. Extroverts.
Make it fun. X% play, 1-X% structured learning.

Feedback: as frequent, as quick and as accurate as possible. Start (very) small, grow complex.
Performance norms
objective norms:
*points (in an actual test/critical setting)
*time
Subjective norms:
*feeling (how well I feel I understand)

Raising your standards:
*&quot;The cleaner&quot; metaphor : how to clean everything. Anything less is unacceptable.
*&quot;The pragmatic&quot; : what are the 20/80. What is essential/superficial.
*&quot;The idealist&quot; : what matters is that I understood. Own judgment of performance more important than  standardized results. Often delusional.

Measuring work.
*pomodoro (ideally group-synchronized)
-&gt;separate work and breaks
-&gt;full focus/full relax
*expected credits

Planning and organization.
What needs to be done? Years, Months, Month, Week, Day.
Think like an investor: you invest time to get knowledge/skills/revenues, etc. Expected outcome is always the first thing to consider: it&#39;s not rational to study 4 hours for 0.5 credits if you can make 2 credits in 8 hours. Prioritize.
*Have a daily/weekly/monthly metric.
-&gt;[Credits/hour]
-&gt;[Revenue (potential or actual)/hour]
If you have 250 hours and 50 credits to do, that means 0.2 credit/hour - or 20 centicredit/hour.
Good metrics help monitor learning, they become a major source of motivation; because the work-reward relationship becomes solid. Avoids frustration. Keep oneself focused.

Deadlines and Parkinson&#39;s law.
Once you have a clear goal, make yourself accountable. Social incentives. Mutual checking.
Give yourself less time.

Not just a to do list, an item list.
List every skill/object that you need to learn. To could be in a cahier. A page, a skill/concept. Tick it once you master it. Or give it a bar every time you go deeper: reward.

Truth is in the sparring.
Most martial arts are utterly useless for self-defense. No grounding in reality: waste of time, fragile. Ju-jitsu. Muay thai. Mma - as realistic as you can make it. Anti fragile (if new technique, then people adapt). Free fight vs. &quot;competition&quot; (with points).
Theory without practice is like a table with two feet: looks perfect until you shake it or look under it.
Tests, exams, exercises. Correction. Feedback. Repeat.

Learn like you needed it today. Record your learning: cahier, photos (white board/sheets), videos. Set up things in such a way that if you needed this information in 10 years, you could find it and understand it in little to no time.

Rehearsal. Repetition. Variation.
Then make it harder than it will be: less time, no help. Make it different - can you find your center of gravity in this novel situation? What if [this] instead of [that]?

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 07 Feb 2016 16:37:10 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://simonjanin.ch/learning/2016/02/07/The-Art-of-Learning.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://simonjanin.ch/learning/2016/02/07/The-Art-of-Learning.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>learning</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>On Predictions and improving one&#39;s rationality</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There’s no chance that the iPhone is going to get any significant market share.
&lt;strong&gt;No chance&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;– Steve Ballmer, Microsoft CEO (2007)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time, Microsoft’s shares were worth $30 USD, while Apple’s shares were worth about $9 USD – although anecdotal, it is funny to note that they are today respectively worth $55 and $105 USD, with Apple worth almost twice as much as Microsoft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Predictions are an integral part of making decisions: they serve the purpose of guiding us through uncertainty.
Steve Ballmer’s prediction had the form of a horrible one: it was an absolute statement. Of course, we don’t know what Steve Ballmer was really thinking at the time; he might have been terrified at the idea of the iPhone becoming successful, but just hid it well during the interview.
It is obvious that he had a very strong incentive, as one of the largest Microsoft shareholders, to say that competitors will fail – but what’s more troubling is that &lt;strong&gt;he might actually have believed what he said&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us make an observation: &lt;code&gt;random processes tend to follow normal (Gaussian) distributions, while biological systems can exhibit both normal and power law distributions.&lt;/code&gt;
Because I have the luxery of being able to speak my mind (contrary to Steve Ballmer) and since I don’t want to look like a fool (like Steve Ballmer did), I used plenty of adverbs to attenuate the strength of my previous statement (i.e. “tend to”, “can exhibit”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While using weakening adverbs lengthen our statements, they protect us from saying utterely wrong things. &lt;code&gt;We should in fact try to give a more probabilistic nature to our opinions and predictions&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is useful to be aware of the type of distribution we are dealing with before making a prediction. That is, if you were to make a prediction about a random or, at least, pseudo-random process; your best bet is probably to simply pick the middle value – which is more likely to become the median.
On the other hand, if you had to make a prediction about a biological phenomena exhibiting network effects, you should pick either one of the extremes that you think is more likely and then weight it against similar phenomena (if there are 10 independent outcomes whose probability is hard to estimate, start by assigning them a 10% probability and then run multiple scenario updating probabilities accordingly).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notwithstanding how crude this heuristic is, it should at least serve as a reminder that it is crucial to minimize biases from partial information, and instead focus on first principles (i.e. which kind of distribution we are likely dealing with and what the baseline is).
Having done this, you can proceed to fine-tuning your predictions and weighting the different factors you consider will have an impact on the result; but this should come second, not first.
Then, make sure that your prediction is inherently probabilistic and doesn’t contain any unnecessary absolute statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us make a small list of principles to abide by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No event that doesn’t break the rules of logic a priori has probability 0% – although it could be as low as &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;10^{-100}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Incompatible events reduce each other’s likelyhood.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the process is akin to a dice roll within a given range, assume a normal distribution. Pick the center as median.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the process is likely to exhibit a network effect (or cumulative effect), consider the possibility of exponential growth or decay (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;e^{\lambda t}, \lambda \in \mathbb{R}&lt;/script&gt;). Pick an extreme and weight it against comparable data.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Predictions should be phrased in such a way that they reflect the nature of the probability distribution we believe fits the data the best. Sentences such as “within the range [a,b]” should be favored over picking exact points in general.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prediction is a human endevour – it is not purely mathematical, or even physical. Be aware of the stance you take and compare the risk times the cost of being wrong to the likelyhood times the payoff of being right.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There are different kinds of predictions: truth-focused, impact-focused and blackswan-focused – the first aims at correctly assessing an event’s likelyhood, the second tries to either change the course of an event while the third takes a bet on an unlikely event where the payout of being right is larger than the cumulative cost of being wrong multiple times (think of economists predicting crashes: huge payout for calling a crisis, little to no costs for being wrong).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To assess someone’s prediction, try to categorize it in one of the three categories given in point 7&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If truth is your goal, avoid absolute statements. Only apodictical propositions can be safely stated in an absolute way.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Whenever there are two competing predictions, favor the simplest (incompetence over maliciousness, normal cases over extremes ones, first principles over anecdotes, natural over surnatural) – which is essentially Occam’s razor.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Predictions should be written down and verified a posteriori and serve as a windows into one’s cognitive biases – this might be an excellent way to improve one’s rationality.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This list may come in handy as predictions become more prevalent, in the… future.
Oh, did I just make an impact and blackswan focused prediction about predictions? This might have gotten unnecessarily meta here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I am excited to soon be able to participate and improve my rationality thanks to Ethereum and blockchain-based predictions markets like Augur and GroupGnosis!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 02 Jan 2016 01:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://simonjanin.ch/rationality/prediction/learning/feedback/2016/01/02/on-Predictions-and-improving-ones-rationality.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://simonjanin.ch/rationality/prediction/learning/feedback/2016/01/02/on-Predictions-and-improving-ones-rationality.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>rationality</category>
        
        <category>prediction</category>
        
        <category>learning</category>
        
        <category>feedback</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Ethereum for Investors, part II -- Opportunities and Risks</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This second video on the series “Ethereum for Investors” was quite fascinating to make!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I discuss the different opportunities and risks in the Ethereum space, with a segway into Proof of Stake; I mention Augur, Slock.it, Digix, HitFin, IPFS and I try to give you an overview that will help you make the right decisions with your time and money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/1bn8Wwbum18&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The PDF of the presentation is &lt;a href=&quot;/downloads/Ethereum_for_Investors-Opportunities_and_Risks.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 18 Dec 2015 18:11:25 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://simonjanin.ch/cryptocurrency/ethereum/2015/12/18/Ethereum-for-Investors-part-II-Opportunities-and-Risks.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://simonjanin.ch/cryptocurrency/ethereum/2015/12/18/Ethereum-for-Investors-part-II-Opportunities-and-Risks.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>cryptocurrency</category>
        
        <category>ethereum</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Proof of Stake based voting system proposal to fund the Ethereum foundation</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Projects of the scale and complexity of Ethereum and Bitcoin are typically subjected to the issue of how to fund them.
The &lt;a href=&quot;http://bitcoinfoundation.org/member/&quot;&gt;Bitcoin Foundation&lt;/a&gt; is funded by a consequent number of actors, some relatively large Bitcoin-based ventures as well as a fair number of individuals.
Nonetheless, as of today, only three members of the Bitcoin foundation are actually paid salaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Ethereum is a very complex project, and it seems obvious that it could not be realized with only three full-time developers -- notwithstanding the large open-source participation it has benefited from, the core development of the platform requires a large focused effort.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been a few proposals on how to fund the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ethereum.org/foundation&quot;&gt;Ethereum foundation&lt;/a&gt; in the future: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sponsorships&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;calls for donation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;creating new ether that would be sold by the foundation (typically in the new genesis block)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;having miners pay a fraction of the mining fees they collected (or of the reward of the block they mined).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those options are not mutually exclusive – although I particularly dislike the third option of artificially increasing supply.
In this article I will explore the last possibility, focusing solely on Proof of Stake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-proposal&quot;&gt;The proposal&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First off, let me say that this would probably not be adapted for Proof of Work – because of the nothing at stake problem; this is why we need Proof of Stake.
Alright, let’s get started!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us introduce the parameter &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p&lt;/script&gt; which is the percentage of the transactions fees that will be donated to the Ethereum foundation (it could apply to the block reward as well, this depends on the actual Proof of Stake implementation, so I will stick to the first option for now).
Each time a new block is generated, that is every 17 seconds as of today, each validator &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;i&lt;/script&gt; of the platform will cast a vote &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;v_{i} \in [0,M]&lt;/script&gt; of weight &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;w_{i}&lt;/script&gt; linearly proportional to its actual bounded stake in the platform in the form of a percentage. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
0 &lt; M \leq 1 %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt; is the maximal allowed value for a vote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vote &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;v_{i}&lt;/script&gt; corresponds to the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p&lt;/script&gt; value that the validator wishes to be enforced. Concretely he would choose &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;v_{i} = 0.00&lt;/script&gt; if he would like &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p&lt;/script&gt; to become &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;0&lt;/script&gt;, while he would select &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
0 &lt; v_{i} \leq 1 %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt; otherwise.
After every validator has voted, the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p&lt;/script&gt; value for the present block is given by simple weighted sum: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p = \sum_{i} v_{i} *w_{i}&lt;/script&gt;. Additionnally, we could limit &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p&lt;/script&gt; within some range, typically &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;0.5&lt;/script&gt; or less.
To make things simpler, a validator casts his vote &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;v_{i}&lt;/script&gt; each time he bonds some stake in the platform, and he can change his vote every &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;T&lt;/script&gt; blocks for &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;T&lt;/script&gt; desirably relatively large but smaller than the bonding time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of limiting this feature to sending transactions fees to the address of the Ethereum Foundation, this could be extended into a full-fledged feature of the validating algorithm – for funding related side projects. This might be interesting; although there are quite a few subtleties that would introduce additional complexity and might divert this proposal from its original purpose. So let us stay focused on our main goal: funding the Ethereum Foundation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;consensus&quot;&gt;Consensus&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This simple tweak would be directly implemented into the Proof of Stake validation algorithm in such a way that each block validator would automatically send &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;1-p\%&lt;/script&gt; of the transactions fees to himself and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p\%&lt;/script&gt; to a smart contract belonging to the Ethereum Foundation. In order for this mechanism to be enforced by all validators, the majority of validators would need to mark blocks that don’t respect this mechanism as invalid.
Obviously, if all validators collude, they could choose not to enforce this mechanism, but they may as well just all vote for &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p=0&lt;/script&gt;, so they have no incentive to game the system (in the form I described above).
The only consensus problem could arise if there are a large amount of altruists, but still more “rational” validators – this is similar to the problem addressed in the next section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;economical-incentives-analysis&quot;&gt;Economical incentives analysis&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far we have only used very simple mathematics. Many different such mechanisms can be conveived of, but we only present the most basic here as it might be good enough.
Let us now see if our proposal is robust in term of incentives.
I generally refer to the Ethereum Foundation here, but this also applies to altruists.
Obviously, since the Ethereum Foundation members as well as the Foundation itself own some Ethers, they could cast the highest vote possible &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;v_{i} = M&lt;/script&gt; every time in order to receive more fees – and as they receive more ether, they could bond more stake in order to increase their voting share, creating a feedback loop. I believe that this isn’t a real issue in practice, and I am sure that the foundation will behave honestly but for the sake of security let us try to mitigate this possibility.
First, we could simply set the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;M&lt;/script&gt; value lower in the validator client implementation, i.e. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;M = 0.25&lt;/script&gt; (this number is very easily verifiable in the source code so there is no incentive to cheat and getting caught in changing it in an update would create a hard fork – so they don’t have an incentive to do this).
Or another mitigation would be to set &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;M&lt;/script&gt; even lower and introduce an additional ceiling &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;C&lt;/script&gt;, where it would be possible to vote above &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;M&lt;/script&gt; but the validator would have to pay &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt; M + C &gt; p&lt;/script&gt; while the other validators who voted &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;v_{i} \leq M&lt;/script&gt; would only pay &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p&lt;/script&gt; – this would furthermore make it possible for altruists to fund the Ethereum Foundation even more generously if they so wish (without forcing others to pay more than &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p&lt;/script&gt;). This last parameter &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;C&lt;/script&gt; makes it not profitable for a &lt;em&gt;potentially malicious&lt;/em&gt; foundation to cheat because in order to cast the recent gains as a vote to increase p, they need to bond this stake; and in the theoretical worst case, they would achieve at most &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;p = M&lt;/script&gt;, although I believe that this might not even be possible to raise it that high in practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, in the theoretical absolute worst case, we only need to have a global minimal consensus that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;0 \leq p \leq M&lt;/script&gt;. Although probably much less in practice, further analysis is required to quantify this precisely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;psychological-layer&quot;&gt;Psychological layer&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a future validator, once we switch to Proof of Stake, I perceive this proposal as a fair balance between subsidizing the Ethereum Foundation and profiting from the transactions fees. Validators benefit greatly from a continuous development of the platform, since the security of their stake depends on it. This symbiotic relationship between the Ethereum Foundation, the core programmers and validators paves the way for a future where each actor wins from the bettermen of the platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the switch to Proof of Stake is something that long-term holders seem to desire, and this way of funding the Foundation would further incentivize the switch to Proof of Stake to happen sooner as well – from which both would benefit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In light of our quick analysis, this mechanism seems to fit nicely into the Proof of Stake system and the incentive structure appears to be pretty robust.
Further analysis is required to precisely determine what the practical consensus upperbound is.
Also, I believe that the community will probably not be opposed to this since every validator has his word, and everyone contributes equally – while altruits are given the possiblity to contribute even more if they wish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said before, this proposal is not mutually exclusive to the other options of funding the Foundation, but this seems the fairest one. No inflation. No secret. No outside influence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am looking forward to reading your comments and suggestions for improving this article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to HodlDwon for bringing up the issue of funding.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2015 22:25:30 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://simonjanin.ch/cryptocurrency/ethereum/2015/12/01/a-PoS-voting-system-to-fund-the-Ethereum-foundation.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://simonjanin.ch/cryptocurrency/ethereum/2015/12/01/a-PoS-voting-system-to-fund-the-Ethereum-foundation.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>cryptocurrency</category>
        
        <category>ethereum</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Ethereum for Investors -- Introduction</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Since my last article on Ethereum, I have diven deep into the platform: I read extensively on the topic and watched countless videos to help me understand the technicalities of the blockchain; this drive translated into the urge to record YouTube videos and to start a channel dedicated to Ethereum and blockchain technologies.
Today, I release a video aimed at potential investors in Ethereum (and the ecosystem around it) – people who are programmers, enthusiasts, newcomers or venture capitalists.
My goal is to make Ethereum accessible to more people, and to help them understand the platform better – especially since so many questions are coming up again and again on reddit and the forums (the issuance model, the applications, smart contracts, DAPPS, Proof of Stake, Regulations, etc.).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/nDY0s_e3n34&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the slides of this presentation &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1h8Ym143zzwRYx2vgLwLw5P_QA2CvKpJOzx_3Tv7xhFE/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next week, I will release a video purely focused on investment: what are the risks and opportunities, how to think about Ethereum and what factors are most important to make good investing decisions. I will also talk specifically about the projects and startups that are flourishing in the Ethereum ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 21 Nov 2015 16:34:30 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://simonjanin.ch/cryptocurrency/ethereum/2015/11/21/ethereum-for-investors.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://simonjanin.ch/cryptocurrency/ethereum/2015/11/21/ethereum-for-investors.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>cryptocurrency</category>
        
        <category>ethereum</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The n-back Challenge</title>
        <description>&lt;iframe width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;900&quot; src=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/15cOSi6QUyg3gW90Kg4hEddKFSo6B6WFYsZMXRCITtS0/pubhtml?gid=859276825&amp;amp;single=true&amp;amp;widget=true&amp;amp;headers=false&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 15 Oct 2015 22:59:50 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://simonjanin.ch/brain-training/dual-n-back/2015/10/15/the-n-back-challenge.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://simonjanin.ch/brain-training/dual-n-back/2015/10/15/the-n-back-challenge.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>brain-training</category>
        
        <category>dual-n-back</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>On Cryptocurrencies: Bitcoin, Ethereum - and how to price them</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve recently discovered &lt;strong&gt;Ethereum&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;code&gt;more than a cryptocurrency, it is a general-purpose Turing-complete blockchain-based platform for hosting decentralized applications&lt;/code&gt;. I had been waiting for something like Ethereum for more than two years, after I realized that the potential of Bitcoin was limited by its inherent weaknesses in term of mining, centralization and incentive structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I had promised myself to seize the next blockchain-based opportunity, and I feel that Ethereum could be it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But its complexity makes it difficult to grasp, so after quite a bit a research I decided to make a video of what I found to help me understand and price Ethereum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/16cSBp2NW3o&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;video-outline&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Video outline&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[0:00]&lt;/strong&gt; Introduction: the various cryptocurrencies&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[1:30]&lt;/strong&gt; Ethereum prices of the last month&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[4:30]&lt;/strong&gt; Market Cap&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[8:20]&lt;/strong&gt; Ethereum mining hypothesis&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[10:40]&lt;/strong&gt; Total Ether supply&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[11:40]&lt;/strong&gt; Block difficulty&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[12:40]&lt;/strong&gt; Refutation of hypothesis&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[14:30]&lt;/strong&gt; An interesting contract…&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[16:30]&lt;/strong&gt; Inside story&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[18:00]&lt;/strong&gt; A convincing prediction&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[19:00]&lt;/strong&gt; Summary&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[22:10]&lt;/strong&gt; Further prediction&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[24:00]&lt;/strong&gt; Speculation and analysis; comparision with Bitcoin&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[27:50]&lt;/strong&gt; Conclusion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[29:00]&lt;/strong&gt; Notes about the potential of Ethereum&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[30:00]&lt;/strong&gt; Personal strategy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/downloads/ethereum.png&quot; alt=&quot;Ethereum&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2015 20:34:30 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://simonjanin.ch/cryptocurrency/ethereum/2015/09/29/on-cryptocurrencies-bitcoin-and-ethereum-and-how-to-price-them.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://simonjanin.ch/cryptocurrency/ethereum/2015/09/29/on-cryptocurrencies-bitcoin-and-ethereum-and-how-to-price-them.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>cryptocurrency</category>
        
        <category>ethereum</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>To solve the Theory of everything, solve AI first</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In this 16 minutes talk, co-founder and CEO of Deepmind (now Google Deepmind) Demis Hassabis presents his ideas and goals on artificial intelligence and learning. He goes on to say that utimately, we need to solve AI to solve the grand questions of humankind - the grandest one being the theory of everything, a perfect physical model of the universe accounting for litteraly &lt;code&gt;everything&lt;/code&gt;. It might indeed take an AI to solve the inconsistencies physicists encounter at sub-nano level at very high energies, since those problems require to both use quantum mechanics and general relativity - which collide in the extreme cases. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/rbsqaJwpu6A&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a Go player, I am tempted to make a prediction on the evolution of computer Go. I have been warned from making such risky predictions, but I feel that even if I turn out to be wrong, I’ll learn from them since I’ll have written them down - this Blog will serve as a track-record for my predictions, and I’m looking forward to seeing how badly I’m wrong in a few years!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I predict that computers will be able to play Go at the professional level within the next 5 years; more precisely, I expect a computer to be able to win at least a game out of four against a professional player with a rank of at least 1p on a 19x19 board with the computer taking black with komi &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\geq 0.5&lt;/script&gt;. This has to happen by 13/09/2020 – Simon Janin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe it’s within reach in 3 years or less, but 5 years seems like a fair bet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/downloads/go-game.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Game of Go&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 13 Sep 2015 22:16:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://simonjanin.ch/ai/learning/2015/09/13/to-solve-the-theory-of-everything-solve-ai.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://simonjanin.ch/ai/learning/2015/09/13/to-solve-the-theory-of-everything-solve-ai.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>ai</category>
        
        <category>learning</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
